Inventory of the West of the Boulevard Civic Association Archives 1964-1995
Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
West of the Boulevard Civic Association Archives 1964-1995
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
M 263
2.6 linear feet
West of the Boulevard Civic Association
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for use without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The collection was originally donated to the Special Collections and Archives Department by Juanita F. Parry of the West of the Boulevard Association in 1979. Additional materials were donated in 1994 and in 1999.
Biographical/Historical Information
The West of the Boulevard Civic Association was organized on November 5, 1964 for the following purposes:
1. To keep out commercial establishments that tend to degrade, disrupt the peace, or have an immoral influence on the neighborhood bounded by the Boulevard on the east, Cary Street to the south, the Belt Line (I-95) on the west, and Broad Street on the north.
2. To upgrade the general appearance and value of real estate in the area.
3. To cultivate the good will of tenants in rental properties to a sense of cooperation and pride in their surroundings.
4. To present programs that are informative, constructive, and stimulating to the association.
The West of the Boulevard Civic Association represents about 5,000 households and businesses in the area bounded by Broad and Cary streets and the Boulevard and Interstate 1-95. The district, an early-century trolley-car suburb, covers 1,763 buildings.
Scope and Content Information
The collection consists of various documents relating to the Board of Directors, members, and special projects of the West of the Boulevard Civic Association ranging in date from 1964-1995, including the West of the Boulevard area designation as a Virginia Historic District.
Arrangement
The papers are arranged alphabetically by category and then chronologically.
Contents List
- Albert H. Hill School 1991 (Box 1)
- Annual Membership Reports 1964-1984 (Box 1)
- Area Data-Maps, Census information 1993 (Box 1)
- Bellmont Library (Box 1)
- Benedictine High School 1924-1987 (Box 1)
- Beth-Elites 1991 (Box 1)
- Board of Directors (Correspondence) 1964-1986 (Box 1)
- Board of Directors 1966-1982 (Box 1)
- City of Richmond Planning Proposals 1972-1978 (Box 1)
- City of Richmond Publications 1973-1975 (Box 1)
- Clean-up Campaigns 1978-1979 (Box 1)
- Commission of Architectural Review, Correspondence and Reports 1989-1993 (Box 1)
- Committee Priorities 1988-1996 (Box 1)
- Correspondence 1972-1992 (Box 1)
- Correspondence and Notes of Ernest C. Vaughn (Box 1)
  Material was originally bound; that order is preserved here
- Correspondence Memos 1989-1993 (Box 1)
- Financial and Treasurer's Report 1965-1979 (Box 1)
- Garden Contest 1982-1983 (Box 1)
- Hermitage Road Historic District Association, February 1993 (Box 1)
- Introduction to David Brown Lecture on Economic Development and Preservation, May 1993 (Box 1)
- May Fair 1976-1980 (Box 1)
- Meetings/Minutes 1981-1992 (Box 1)
- Membership Reports, Lists of Members 1965-1981 (Box 1)
- Minutes of Annual Meetings 1965, 1973-1976 (Box 1)
- Minutes: Membership Meetings 1980-1990 (Box 1)
- National Register of Historic Places, Fan Area District 1984-1992 (Box 1)
- Newsletters 1974-1986 (Box 1)
- Newsletters 1987-1991 (Box 1)
- Newsletters 1992-1993 (Box 2)
- Newsletters 1994-1995 (Box 2)
- Newspaper and Journal Clippings 1992-1993 (Box 2)
- Notices to Members 1964-1981 (Box 2)
- Other Civic Associations 1964, 1975 (Box 2)
- Pictures to Support Neighborhood Needs 1984 (Box 2)
- Planning and Land Use Committee 1969-1974 (Box 2)
- Saint Gertrude 1989 (Box 2)
- Streetscapes of West of the Blvd. Area (Box 2)
- Traffic Study 1974 (Box 2)
- Urban Design Proposals for the West of the Blvd. Neighborhood (Box 2)
- Virginia Department of Historic Resources 1993 (Box 2)
- West of the Boulevard Civic Association Newsletter 1991-1993 (Box 2)
- West of the Boulevard Design Overlay District (Project Papers) (Box 2)
- West of the Boulevard Design Overlay District Proposal April 9, 1996, 1997 (Box 2)
- West of the Boulevard Historic District, Proposal history, News Releases 1991-1993 (Box 2)
- 2900 Kensington Ave. Johnston-Willis Hospital Building 1991 (Box 2)
- 3201 Grove Avenue-(Paul Harris House) or (Wendall Powell House) 1911-1977 (Box 2)